so let's start with a question
um does meditation lead to the sensation
of
craving or does one need to understand
the sensation of craving in order to
meditate
l so then why do the Su say that for
example um like why is it that only aun
is free from
craving because that's the argument that
people would make that you know even if
for example somebody becomes a satop
gets the Right View understand for no
the truths they're not fully free from
craving until they become going
around yeah but then there is a
distinction between being fully free
from craving which is the art and
actually rightly seeing that craving is
the origin of
suffering uh right so then so but does
that mean that when you have understood
that craving is the ordinary suffering
your practice
like you cannot help but do the practice
with craving but that is now the next
craving but that is now the next
question yeah like so when someone has
rightly understood for himself this
formable truths right which is like
craving is the origin of
suffering then it is based upon that
Insight that basically the Noble eful
Path arises which is the foundation of
the way the Buddha discusses let's say
medit
um so that would be the distinction
there but then to say that that one is
making progress along the Noble atal
Path based on craving would be
contradicting that very Insight which is
the formable truth namely that craving
is the origin of suffering yeah because
if you have if you have understood the
sensation of craving actually which is
the understanding of the then why would
you keep out of it
knowingly with the excuse that you know
it's the force that propels you in the
practice Yeah so quite the contrary uh
it seems to me then the understanding
would be that you want to avoid acting
out of craving which is how you make
progress along the over path but so
then what if then somebody
says uh well but how can you make effort
like if you just give up all craving
then you just don't do anything and you
just sit they're kind of dead yeah that
is how it would seem for someone then
who has not let's say fully understood
these vulnerable truths to the point
that the no a path Ares they they they
cannot help then it seems to me but
think in terms of craving but what we
could do is take that as a starting
point let's say the ordinary SP
perspective take a peak let's say Beyond
the fence so to speak and try to find
out what are then if it's not craving
that is the determining factor for
Progress along the no AAL path can we
then clarify which factors allow that Noble
clarify which factors allow that Noble
disciple to become an yeah but before we
get into that just to to show kind of
the the fallacy of the view that I just
mentioned well if giving up craving
means that you don't do anything and
you're just there not not practicing at
all then how is it that Anar continues
to like how is it that the Buddha was
able to teach who knows how many
thousands of discourses and you know
make effort to have his dama be
understood and and you know um ah so
you're asking how can there be effort
without craving exactly so because
people would say no no but how are you
going to give up craving when you're not
an Arun if that means that you won't be
able to practice towards arship
yeah yeah yeah so how can there be
effort without craving yeah this is
another question yeah so so
because that's exactly as you said from
the point of view of an ordinary person
they cannot separate uh
intention from craving it seems like
it's necessary necessarily bound up
together and uh and so unfortunately
then you know most approaches to
meditation today kind of instead of
pushing people to develop their View and
see that those things can and should be
separated it's like no no no it's okay
you just need to find a better type of
craving a better type of delight a
better type of of um you know
attachment that's going to like you know
progressing and refining your
attachments until you have no
attachments yeah meanwhile you keep
justifying just that same craving and
attachment in the name of refining it
and as long as you keep justifying it
you're not abandoning it yeah the thing
is you you know already that it's un
wholesome or like you know already that
you're acting out of attachment so
whatever attachment is left there for a
noble disciple that he doesn't
understand or that he hasn't seen for
himself it's there because he hasn't
seen it not because he's telling to
himself oh yes I know that it's there
but you know because for now I'm a noble
disciple I won't deal with thish no it's
precisely because he's not aware of it
that he hasn't dealt with it but no
these people are saying no no I'm fully
aware that these whole janas and
meditation and everything is just
Delight in in you know in Sensations and
stuff even and yet you know it's fine
because thanks to this I don't give into
the sensual coar things in the external
world that I used to get into yeah but
that's quite quite a point because in
this kind of view like that implies that
the object is the problem and as long as
you keep refining the object that's fine
because eventually the object becomes so
refined that craving is not there
anymore and that totally Overlook the
fact that craving is an attitude towards
the object exactly then like if actually
if you maintain the view that the object
is a problem freedom is impossible
because it will always be an object and
that's pretty much why you know in with
this kind of view you know the they
would try to kind of lay out the path
like how it's going to pan out in the
end but very rarely do you actually see
that they say no no I know for myself
that that's going to be you know that
that this craving is going to disappear
eventually it's kind of Taken on faith
that by just refining it and refining
and refining it uh it's it's going to uh
fade away eventually but like very
rarely would you be able to see someone
who says no no I know for myself that by
taking this route craving has actually
faded away and that's because that's not
how it works like you cannot
um like dividing something by two or by
whichever number an infinite amount of
times still leaves you with something
yeah so um the the as you said it's the
attitude of craving the attitude of
expectation the attitude of wanting that
needs to be put in question and um it's
uh it's by recognizing that as the issue
that you would abandon craving so that
that then leads to the the next Point
what did the Buddha say is the origin of
craving in the most fundamental sense is
it just an energy that's that's kind of
there on its own kind of like P primary
to everything else or does it have a um
kind of fundamental basis
feeling uh more
fund ignorance yeah exactly so that's
that's a point that's over
there craving is there and everything in
the the the whole um mass of suffering
the whole factors is there because ignorance
whole factors is there because ignorance
is there so then it's not a matter of
like oh craving is there because I
haven't practiced for 20 years like
destroying this energy that's there
little by little no if you were to stop
being ignorant today you would have no
craving today so because craving is like
today so because craving is like
ignorance creates a space for
craving so when that space is not there
then CRA that's the only way to like you
have to remove the space where craving
kind of finds an entry not like deal
with the craving itself and try to to
diminish it so that's why the Buddha
said um it's with the with the arising
with the complete feding away of
ignorance which was the root of
everything everything
else gets destroyed like a kind of a
series of dominoes or something so in
the context of the pation yeah
exactly so that's that's where um because
so that's that's where um because
usually yeah when it's because kind of
the the common denominator most of the
time is the management then what you're
really confusing with craving or what
you think is craving is more like how do
I refine my feelings mhm how do I make
them smaller and smaller until you know
there isn't craving because you have
managed your feeling so well not because
you have actually Abed the liability to
craving by abandoning ignorance MH
so um having said
that what does it mean
to understand the sensation of crav like
is that poof an experience that you had
one day and oh wow I saw the sensation
of craving and then it's like like this
how how do they call that uh fruition
experience or something like you get it
once and then if you have that kind of
memory or whatever that's your stream
entry yeah and then you've got all the
review knowledges based on that and then
before you know if you're properly lost
in the commentaries but if you get
Alzheimer's then everything is gone yeah
because you forgot the experience yeah
so that's a bit of a dubious take on the
whole that it seems to me so what does
it mean then to understand sensation of
graving because actually the the the
sutas would
say we we did a talk on that one already
where where it says the two type of
meditation the tamed horse and the
untamed horse and it says that the tamed
horse is like just watching the hay and
then the untamed horse asks himself what
does the trainer want me to do today
that's it's other way around the untamed
horse is what's in the okay yeah and
yeah but then later on when it talks
about um what does it
mean like the the thorough breaths
meditation as it says there yes it says
it's not dependent on air water
fire U on earth water fire air uh on
this what's seen heard cognized
dependent on anything basically and then
it says at the end um that even the gods
don't know on what basis that meditation
proceeds yes and
so that kind of hints at the point of
that sensation sensation of craving how
that is the right meditation not that
that's the result that that like later
on that's magically going to happen to
you no no you need to have that
recognition of how to meditate like the
Thor bread m in order to be meditating
rightly yes so
so what does that mean then sensation of
craving sensation of dependence
dependencies sensation of attachment you
can
say kind of practically
speaking the way understand it anyway
will be that whenever I see myself
craving for something will be to
actually restrain myself from acting out
of that very craving because as long as
I'm acting out I feel the same attitude
and then the sensation is impossible
because I am feeding it by acting out of
it so in order to see the sensation I
have to kind of allow it to happen in a
way that I don't act out otherwise if
I'm acting out that's kind of impossible
kind of imply that I keep ring with it
basically so so is it just to stop
giving into it like just stop giving to
it and that's it or is it and to not try
and get rid of it the middle way of yeah
not acting out of it not trying to get
rid of it because you can also go to The
Other Extreme of uh denying it trying to
to yeah imply that it shouldn't be there
which is also c yeah so but then um so
in order to give up some that you were
acting out of do you need to have
something else motivating you like do
you need to have a prize at the end to
say like oh if I give this up I will
receive this
reward no what is the already is a
broader context so what is there already
is for example the fact that your body
is that you're that you're sitting or
you're standing you're in a posture or
that you're um breathing or so there is
already a context there not not in time
that you have to achieve somehow in the
future there is already you find
yourself in this in you find this
broader context already there that that
you do not need to achieve in the future
exactly so meaning that is absent from
craving if you're so meaning
um if
you like you cannot say that
in order to give up one drug you need to
take up another drug yeah for sure you
just see that the fact that as you said
you're already subject to this body
you're already confined with this
experience that's not in your
control that in of itself means that
giving into craving is not a good
idea not not because like I'm going to
get this other reward which I won't get
if I act out of craving it's just no in
and of itself craving is not beneficial
so then
uh strictly speaking this whole idea of
like I need to refine it with the next
thing and with the next thing no like
you recognize your drug is is harming
you and then based on that
recollection that this is not for my
welfare you give it up not on the basis
of like I want this other thing that's
better than this
so that leads us then to the next point
which you should brushed on
before what is it that
would drive your progress if it isn't
craving MH yeah now we I've had that
MH yeah now we I've had that
question if one has understood that
craving is the origin of suffering and
always un wholesome and that even
logically it's a contradiction to say
based on the formable truths that with
craving I'm going to make the ending of
craving then what is it that propels
that Noble disciple let's say along the
Noble eful Path
H just one thing that came to mind is
just like if one seees that craving
actually is the root of suffering he
actually see that acting out of craving
is painful and that recognition itself
seeing that acting out of craving is
painful is enough to not act out of
craving which make him progress but then
if he still accidentally slips up here
or there then what would then then what
would happen how would that be regarded for
happen how would that be regarded for
somebody who actually sh shame and
regret and like kind of yeah just feel
bad about it basically well that's
exactly it so when the that's one of the
factors like when the Buddha discusses
factors of no C I mean there's various
lists and and and
contexts but there are several ones that
always start with this is the hiri and
the OTA right the let's say the the the
healthy shame healthy shame and fear of
of wrongdoing um and so to say well to
still go back to the craving this is
below me this is low I've already
understood that it is that it is that it
is not
worthwh um then it is then it is that
factor or that faculty which is now
based on the right understanding that
will prevent him from not doing it again
which is the
progress and uh what is actually the
Buddha gave a specifically about this
topic he said um give a simly about
somebody who wants to go to a park and
then for as long
as they haven't reached that Park they
would still
have you could say the motivation to
reach that Park once they reached it
they don't longer have that motivation
so so there is one thing or let's say a
group of things that the Buddha talked
about as factors of the path that are
not craving craving is not included in
them yeah but he said if somebody
develops them and makes much of them um
they would become permanently
established in the sensation of craving
completely so what are those things
uhhuh you to
fact uh no not not specifically
it's a bit of a more of an academic
question so it's it's the you know the
four quote unquote spir spiritual Powers
uhuh the first one of which
is go
desire Chand and so yeah but that is but you
Chand and so yeah but that is but you
see the Chanda is not now the tan
exactly yeah so that's the point I'm making see
yeah so that's the point I'm making see
so then there's even there's even a su
where the bu is
saying that he's going through the janas
or I think SAR put is going through the
janas and then he's kind of analyzing
the factors of each J and all of them
basically have Chanda in them but none
of them have craving yeah of course so
uh the point being
Chanda I mean even even the even was
because I mean how how would you
otherwise you know have any interest in
teaching people how would you otherwise
have interest in going for arms round
how would you have interest in like I
don't know your cie braks and you had to
fix it or something um so jand simply
means like um you could translate as
interest or
motivation uh but uh it's not it's not
uh unlike ignorance it doesn't depend on
craving sorry unlike craving it's not
founded upon ignorance yes so there can
be Chanda even though there isn't
ignorance yes now of course so it's a
wholesome motivation pretty much yeah so
when we talk about this like what you
said oh you recognize that acting out of
craving is not for your not for your
welfare you want to give that up that
would be a form of Chanda now taking it
up to the like beyond what it needs to
be and saying oh no it's because I want
this specific thing this specific
experience or whatever now you're
falling into craving and um there's even
that suta where I think we briefly
discussed it in you know the previous
talks that says um that famous verse
that says uh don't long for the past
don't long for the future what is
presently Arisen uh he he clearly sees
he clearly sees unwavering unfaltering
yeah and so in the description there it
says if somebody is longing for the past
for the Aggregates like the way their
Aggregates were in the past yes and they
Delight in that then that's um it says
so that's running after the past and
then if somebody has a desire for the
Aggregates to be a certain way in the
future doesn't matter which way that in
itself is another form of delight
craving you could say then if in the
present they're not clear here about as
it says U unlighted ordinary person
doesn't understand form as not self
feeling is not self form is not self
then they're moved by things in the
present and so that whole discourse is
basically saying in order to practice
rightly you need to abandon all these
anticipations of like what experience
you will have what's kind of what will
come after this when I give all this up
the goal is right now what is there this
feeling that it has arisen this pressure
that has arisen this craving that has
arisen don't act out of it and don't
give into it and then if this kind of
Desire arises like oh oh what's going to
come after I want this or I want that or
maybe this is is that going to be theana
that I read about in the sutas or
whatever well that's now something
that's presently Arisen and if you give
into that now again you're acting out of
craving yeah so that's how you keep
yourself balanced and that's how you are
basically while being effortful and
diligent you're also
patient that's how there ceases to be a
kind of discrepancy between those two
because you know for people it would
seem like Oh either I am just like fired
up craving really hard for this yeah
arship or whatever or I'm just I don't
care about it I just give it up and I'm
content with being a penist sort of
divine laziness which is missing the
yeah but no here is no you
recognize uh the point of diligence but
you don't overstep you recognize there
is a need for diligence but it applies
to what is presently Arisen not for you
to try to get things that you don't have
MH even if it's experiences or to get
rid of things that happen to be the case
exactly for that matter yeah because
then as as it says while you're moved by
Form feeling perception that has arisen
trying to get rid of it is another form
of taking it as mine because otherwise
why would you try to modify something if
you know that it doesn't belong to you
now would you say that this is the that
this could be a description of the
thorough breaths meditation on how it
doesn't depend pretty much yeah exactly
yeah that you could make that connection
but um the important point is is to
recognize that well that in itself could
be a a
contemplation that if somebody really
kind of um takes it to the full extent
obviously on the basis of training on a
practical level of virtue sensor
restraint and and The Graduate training
uh that they try to differentiate how
can I have Chanda how can I have an
interest how can I have uh motivation
for practice without it being craving
yes and so uh for as long as you don't
have the right view yet that will has to
seem to some extent as a
paradoxical um
situation but um then when it when you
actually understand craving you see oh
well this was redundant all along there
was no need for this so the CH survives
the forming way of the craving exactly
yeah and
so that's that's the the um the the
entire piece that that the that the
Buddha talks about like the seven
Enlightenment factors it says dependent
on sensation dependent on withdrawal
dependent on dispassion MH so he
develops and then it goes to all these
factors yeah so all of that already like
all the peace that Cal The Joy all of
that already depends on you giving up
craving yes cuz there is no other type
of happiness or or pleasure that can be
wholesome if it's bound up with craving
yeah it's un wholesome for the very
reason yeah
so that's
the um the the main thing to recognize as
um the the main thing to recognize as
well is
um you cannot
justify any recog any you can you cannot
justify any instance of craving if
you're aware of it there will be things
that you know inevitably especially if
you haven't trained and you
know the the gradual refinement that
does happen is a refinement of grad
training like we spoken about before but
that's a refinement of understanding not
not like making the crav more exactly
exactly so yeah if you haven't refined
that then for sure there will be
instances of craving that even if you
try you won't have recognized them but
um the stuff that you do recognize like
if you break a precept you don't like oh
I mean this is fine or something later
I'll give it up no if you're aware of it
the diligent thing to do is to restrain
it and prevent it from prevent the
transgression from occurring yeah that's
already a good attitude to have from the
beginning and then there's also this one
discourse in the ma right in fact says
that if a noble disciple would
transgress training rules he would not
leave them if it's does that he would
not leave them unome precisely because
he now understands that you cannot break
the important ones without having been
craving involved yeah so that's bound up
with this uh with this uh healthy sense
of basically shame and fear knowing that
that goes against that principle which
has now been understood you at least for
yourself you you don't want to have that
situation then uring that would be a bit
of a
contradiction and
um the thing is there's even this suta
where um it it is kind of a late suta and some
um it it is kind of a late suta and some
Scholars argue that maybe it can ler but
the principle is perfectly sound um this
grade 40 Su that says like there's a a
right speech Right View mundane Right
View and sear mundane Right View mundane
right intention separ mundane right
intention um the Curious Thing is it
doesn't go all the way it doesn't say
that there is mundane right effort and
SE mundane right effort or mundane right
mindfulness and SE mundane right
mindfulness it stops at right livelihood
H um so it's not that you have like
mundane right of that's that's a
contradiction in terms uh but um the
point there being it says when a noble
disciple is practicing right speech
practicing right action it says he does
so with a mind that's free from the
fits mhm at that moment yes so that's
the that's the the critical thing to see
like um
it's the
liability to the
fs that a noble disciple hasn't
overcome but the third Noble Truth as
it's defined even in the sutas it's the
remainder fading way of
craving so it's basically just that they
haven't been
established in that but they know the
full sensation exactly yeah and and
there's even another s that says what is
the right the right practice and the
wrong practice and then the right
practice or the right path it says with
ignorance um activities with activities
Consciousness and basically lists the in
the normal that's the wrong path that's the
normal that's the wrong path that's the
wrong path yes then the right path it
says the path it says with the remainder
lless fading away of ignorance there is
sensation of activities sensation of
activities uh sensation of Consciousness
yeah in other words that's that's the path
in other words that's that's the path
yeah so can we say that there is this
General principle that in the suas they
also talk about development right or or
B like there's many suas which has know
develops Enlightenment factors or noal
path and that it's very easy to assume
that the development is always positive
going towards something based ulon
whereas um the whole dharm has this
negative uh it's Timeless as we yeah
it's Timeless but it's got this negative
B not negative in the sense that it is
depressing or anything it's not an
emotional connotation but negative that
is based upon sensation giving up
dispassion relinquishment and so by not
falling back into the craving which is
the positive thing that you abandon and
by the abandoning you make progress
towards the complete sensation of
suffering yeah so that is sort of a
negative progress so to speak but that
is the only progress from the point of
view of the noble D but that requires
now a shift in understanding because
words like progress and development in
all mundane Affairs are always like I
make an effort now in order to get
something in the future and then you are
already in this sort of time bound way
of thinking which is which is like may
my Aggregates in the future be like this
or like that and then and then you're
basically done yeah that's that's the
when the suit somebody would tell like a
mon tell them oh you should this R
because you're kind of chasing after
something that takes time while
sensuality and worldly things are just
available right in the present and he
would say no it's the opposite like
sensuality takes time the dhma is always
presently applicable
so um it's important to see then that
meditation and I mean there's a reason
why they s to say the no wful path is
acquired by a
so it's important then to recognize the
goal should be understanding you will
only arrive at the sensation of at the
understanding of the sensation of
craving if you're trying to understand
the sensation of craving whereas the
usual view is I do this technique I do
this method and then by doing the same
thing as a result as a result so it's
kind of like the saying it says like
doing the same thing and expecting
different results yeah it's the
definition of Madness yeah I think it
was Einstein who said that no yeah so so
you're not you you might get a special
result that doesn't mean it's different
from like it's special compared to what
you're used to but it's not special like
you're you're still within the same
overall overarching view of what the
practice is and what's important and
what's not important so you're not
unless you're trying to to understand
you're not going to progress to its
understanding like nobody just I don't
know spends their time cooking expecting
that that's going to result in tomorrow
being a good
pilot no so only you know sitting at the
cockpit messing around with the
knowledge that you don't know what
you're doing um over would eventually
results in you being a good pilot so you
through trial and error
reading the sutas uh making effort to
contemplate you understand what this
decision or craving is and then you can
practice meditation because then it's
just like how do I um kind of
focus my energy on just developing that
principle not just on the level of
keeping the precepts and stuff but even
on a mental level now in relation to the
five hindrances even there now I don't
act out of cra
um so that would be the right meditation
where it says after a noble disciple
acquires the seven alignment
factors then he then he can then he has
access to bavana or development yeah so
we should clear up that bavana which
means like development or cultivation
fully depends on the Right View and so
in the context of the sutas strictly
pertains to Noble ones yeah the problem
but the reason the particular reason for
that is now you can start to see it's
not because it's just like a kind of um
like some arbitrary Gateway like no only
so the buters are allowed here you
cannot pass it's because if you don't
understand the station of craving um
because again craving is not like a
switch that's on or off for as long as
there's ignorance craving is there one
way or another so through not
understanding what craving is any
development that you try to do
will be based will be based on craving
no and craving as well yeah of course
yes so so you cannot
develop until you have kind of acquired
the vision of what right development is
yes now can we say that that vision and
and the suas do speak about you know
acquiring vision of dhama which is like
the right view can we say that that's
niana already well yeah I mean there Su do
already well yeah I mean there Su do
that say that that um Noble de
understands Nana sees Nana uh
so the obviously because there are so
many now um mystical views about like
what theana is yeah but as a Buddha
would say is the destruction of uh
passion destruction of aversion and
destruction of
delusion destruction of craving as well
yeah and because he sees that the do
also say he can practice the straight
path like he's not going like like this
because he knows where the sensation of
where the full sensation of suffering
takes place because he understands Right
Here and Now what is the sociation of
suffering yeah yeah it's not like like
an FR experience that you close your
eyes sit there for two hours and okay I
got Nana again uhhuh uh it's it's
whenever you're going walking sitting
lying down abandoning passion a verion
and delusion um regard to what's seen
heard taste cognize
uh sensed planned expected
anticipated um abandon praying in any
instance that's what Nana is and that is
and that is what the right meditation
would be as well yeah exactly so only
then once you have
understood how to
be like you go as we said before you go
this way you're acting under a craving
you go this way you're acting out a
crave but you're also not standing still
now exactly yeah so inevitably PJ is is
be going one of those two routes yeah as
the Buddha said so only by understanding
the middle way which is as the Buddha
said but only then can you can your
but only then can you can your
development not be based on CV on giving
up grading your development would not be
based on oh would not be based on
grading exactly yeah yeah
so the link between keeping the precepts
and sense
restraint and
nibana becomes very clear with that
understanding well yeah
because to the to like it is a a
extinguishment uh quenching of craving
on that level on that level yeah yeah
and then there's more fine levels
there's the mental level the verbal
level so quite the opposite from being
like you're Shifting the craving you're
removing the craving in in more refined
levels yeah instead of bringing the
craving with you you pe it
off but I think many schools of Buddhism
would see their practice
as the um
as yeah moving towards the cessation of
craving but they just have an
inaccurate designation of what craving
is exactly yeah they're consciously
saying oh we're keeping craving going
they they think they're not but they
just haven't understood what craving is
fundamentally you cannot gradually move
towards the sensation of
suffering that's the that's the
contradiction that needs to be realized
so either the sensation of suffering is
fully understood right now or else you
haven't understood it but if you're then
going to gradually go there that's why
you take a long turn so you so so so
what if somebody's
contemplation just squeezes out time all
together so you're basically going to
say all the is is this five Aggregates
all of this experience has has arisen
what is now fundamentally the problem
with just
this would such reflection go anywhere
based upon what we have now just
discussed there might still be this
pressure to envisage a future where
where um I am in the state of Nana but
then you have to include that in the
fact that that is present it's
impossible for that not to be right now
yeah yeah any any vision of the future
so somebody includes that as
well which means some long income comes
up may I which is a bit dubious but okay
that's also understood you include that
because that is just otherwise now as
well so then what you just recognize
that understand that as you just
explained then all there is is what we
find now five agates doing their own
thing what's the point with
that well you asking like what the
practice is there from that position or
yeah if if
somebody questions himself like that
well then there will be the mind trying
to get you to Crave or the mind will be
at some point dragging you towards ill
will or greed or distraction and that is
the practice then then that is that is
then whether you're aware of it or not
you have a choice to to see that as
craving or to act out of it MH and that
yeah so it's not it's not like you're in
a position as you describe of um of
being an outad there is
ignorance there is beginning this that
one finds on in sure but ignorance can
also be dispelled otherwise you would be
lost otherwise you would be lost forever
but we have said that um that in a sense
craving involves time and so we have
taken the route of craving but I'm now
trying to find out if we just take time
as a factor and we're just going to stay
with what
is I would say that the thing is that
could easily also get drift into the
direction of mystification sure because
yes you can well going back to that sud
that we just talked about you can kind
of dismiss the the P the past you can
dismiss the future but in relation to
the present that's that's precisely
where it says uh uninstructed ordinary
person who hasn't seen the noal ones
takes form itself takes feeling itself
so that's like the last part that you
cannot really uh P go past without the
Right View so the the person can give up
expectation of like Nana or whatever but
then they would fall into the view of
glorifying the present moment M of like
saying like oh yeah I'm perfectly
content with what is there now the
present just this is just this uh and
and ironically then that's overshooting
the mark Cuz now they're kind of
pretending like there isn't an mhm that
everything is just fine yeah but that's
not the case and why does that happen
well again because they went in that
direction of
development pretty much instead of the
direction of clarifying their views
before they even try to you know go into
these more subtle aspects of um giving
rise to the joy of the present moment or
whatever U again only when you have
understood how to not have craving would
that thing
with any any kind of um ration of such
kind be
wholesome so as as the Buddha said it's
whether it's um tiny bit of excrement or
whether it's a lot all of it smells the
same way so whether it's a tiny bit of
craving that you're acting out of or a
lot of it none of that is in a way of
path yeah so that can be craving also to
just stay with what is just to be clear
yeah yeah exactly so everything I just
described like it's it's not that if you
just stay with what is and you sort of
abandon the past and you abandon the
future that craving is only in the past
and in the future no on the contrary it
can also be in in relation to what is
that Su that you were referring about
then says and he sees with clear
understanding this has a wisom yeah so
then he he also abandons passion for the
present he doesn't take refuge in the
present that some people would say yeah
exactly like take refuge in the present
moment or something
so
um which is kind of a contradiction term
because it's like oh I go back to the
present moment but that implies that you
run away from from where from you come
from if you go back to something you're
conceiving the
person and uh actually I was going to
bring this up before but um I forgot
about it there's one suta that says um
based on craving one abandons craving in
the same way it says based on food when
abandons food um based on what was the
other one I don't remember the other one but I
one I don't remember the other one but I
think it was three of them uh and it
says but then it gives a description it
doesn't say like based on the no wful
path based on practicing somebody that's
still rooted in craving he gives with
craving it says here somebody hears such
and such a person has become a nor
and then on account of that craving
arises in him to make progress towards
that state now when he kind of starts in the
state now when he kind of starts in the
beginning yes everything will be ring
craving he's going to be visiting the
Buddha asking information trying to
clarify things there's going to be a lot
of restlessness a lot of doubt and all
of that is craving but for that moment
that craving is kind of um setting the
basis for to begin the practice now when
it comes to him actually understanding
the practice if he wants to become a he
needs to understand the station of pray
yes so it's not saying like
um it's not saying like that that's just
going to continue forever or something
no that's that's what puts you kind of
like in the vicinity of the D it's
almost Faith basically like if he could
do it I can do it so so let me crave or
make effort but then that Faith needs to
be upgraded that understanding of
craving needs to be upgraded but but
something is planted there basically
yeah and so then he would if he gets the
Right View then he would understand oh
yeah that craving uh initially led me or
in order to get the right view he would
have to understand yeah that craving
initially led me to want to practice but
now as I said before I need to be able
to separate this
craving throw that away and just keep
the motivation for practice keep the
diligence but without the need for that
craving yeah and that is the
understanding that needs to arise
basically yeah only with understanding
it's not going to be something that
happens by itself because as we said the
whole craving is based on ignorance yeah
so um so yeah that's why that that s has
been taken out of context that people
just say oh yeah based on craving you
abandoned craving but they don't read
like the the next part that say yeah so
so it might be valid let's say from the
very beginning but it cannot be used as
a justification on the noble AAL path
nor even to get to the right view
because that is already based on
understanding that craving is the
original exactly because why would you
be like oh no I know that this is
suffering but I'm okay with it yeah
that's yeah that that's if if truly your
goal is the ending of suffering you
wouldn't have that attitude like oh I
know that this giving me cancer and I
want I'm trying to give a cancer but no
it's fine I'll keep it there for now
yeah but so can we say that uh with the
craving there is an action there is a
evolutional energy whereas with the
Chanda it's
um yeah it's less it's less
uh this action is less uh how can I say
yeah you mean the intensity the
intensity of the action yeah the the the
well in the sense Al when it say that um
there is no more action it just uh let
let uh yeah you find it there and uh so is
uh yeah you find it there and uh so is
there yeah I'm not clear about the
difference between this so yeah would be
a good thing to clarify so what do you
think would be like a good measure of
just some example of an action when it's
just Chanda and when it's just when it's
actually craving yes how would you be
able to tell for yourself because
externally it might look the same like
some people might say oh some people
even blame the Buddha the Aesthetics and
stuff when he saw when they saw him
eating like normal food they thought oh
he's just acting out of crave so since
you cannot measure it by the external
standards necessarily unless the person
is like breaking precepts and stuff how
would you be able to tell for yourself
internally what is more like just Chanda
and what is clearly
CRA I don't know because in one sense if
you see that it's craving you are
understanding it and so you are going
more towards CH but uh there is urance
what is what is there when there is
craving and the the the action the
wanting the the the pressure and and how
has that felt unpleasant yeah so there
is suffering so in other words when
there is craving as always there's going
to be suffering so the main kind of
practical rule of thumb would be if
something's rooted in craving or if you
have a desire let's say you have a an
interest to do something if that
interest is infected with
craving the the effect of that is going
to be if you don't do it you're going to
suffer yes if it's just Chanda then you
don't do it you're not going to it's not
going to be a big deal because there is
no passion involved because there is a
but that's how you would measure the
presence of passion or not like not by
necessarily kind of
how um like the external qualities of
the action let's say
like uh how much you did or how much
effort you put in it's more like how
much would you have suffered if you
couldn't do it so like and that is on
the level of reflection it's not that
you actually need to do it or not do it
that's that's already secondary yeah it
would be based on pretty much
recognition and self honesty like this
mind is like like a like a trained
animal MH like you know it wants to kind
of get up and do something but if you
don't let it it's not that it's going to
start barking at you and and and stuff
so that would be one practical way to
realize like you know as a Buddha would
say eating just for the sake of
sustaining the body for example or using
the lodgings or using the robe just for
the sake of uh the minimal survival MH
then that would be like oh you know am I
having would I be bothered if I can't
eat today would I be or would I be bothered
today would I be or would I be bothered
if I can't get the food that the
specific food that I want to get
mhm and then
see even if the answer is no and the
mind doesn't really care that doesn't
mean that you wouldn't still try
to find something to eat the point being
if you don't get it anything you're not
going to suffer and that's that's the
poems and the sutas it would say like
the monks back in the day like whether
he get something in on own round or not
he he wouldn't he wouldn't be affected
yeah there's this line I'm not sure how
accurately it is translated but it says
somewhere he expects only what is
given but you don't know of course
beforehand what is given so how so how
can you expect it so that's that's
that's a nice way of putting it yeah cuz
you could say oh look he went to get it
so how can that not be rooted in craving
MH but that's because again it's not
rooted in that external kind of
qualities of the action it's internally
how much was
he uh emotionally invested in a certain
outcome let's say and that's where the
ignorance is reflected cuz if you
ignorance being let's say
fundamentally U taking things in mind
not understanding the lack of
ownership um
any suffering to any extent is going to
be rooted in the fact that you you you
took something as yours MH which could
be for example this very body yeah if
you take it as yours then the whole
relationship of food which is what this
body depends upon becomes problematic
but now imagine that it is to the extent
that it can be imagined that this body
is not yours then how does that affect
your relationship to food to its
necessity to the sensuality that is
bound up with it all those actions all
those Cravings in relation to food will
undergo let's say radical shift because
you now see that that has only value in
relation to this body which is seen as
not yours yeah so that's where the
contemplation of
anata would have a valid or like a
tangible effect it's not just a
philosophical idea it's precisely in
this context of does the mind actually
have these desires and obsessions still
or not yeah and with rope and lodgings
is of course also directly bound up with
with with having a body because you want
to protect yourself from elements from
sun heats animals and stuff which is
what the loging does lodging is
basically sort of a further extension of
your rope your rope you have on you but
then you go into the lodging for further
protection but it's the same
principle yeah
so yeah to the extent that you're
understood to the extent that you're not
ignorant about things not being yours
you will not suffer when you don't get
what you want yeah even if you tried to
get it with Chanda even if be yeah
that's it yeah